{
  "reference_number": "12503",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "However, I believe the target should be set for 2040"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2040"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The target should be able to be revised only if the government decides it must reach the net zero target sooner to meet international\n agreements. The target should not under any circumstances extend beyond 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Any changes must improve outcomes by reducing emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only if it wishes to make modifications that will allow NZ to meet its target more quickly."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I don't agree entirely. I believe that effects on the natural environment including ecosystems must also be a factor. Also, the extent to\nwhich decisions will adversely impact pollution or emissions globally. We should not be able to export our emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Of course there must be a clear plan to achieve budgets/targets and it should be assessed by an independent panel of experts to\nensure the plan can achieve set targets/budgets"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We will not meet targets if government selectively listens to business lobbies and government entities focussed on economic\n\ngrowth. Net zero targets must take precedence over short-term economic growth. Therefore Government should hear from local\nauthorities, Greenpeace, Forest and Bird, scientists and the wider community to ensure we are on track to achieve targets. Also, I\nbelieve that effects on the natural environment including ecosystems must also be considered. These considerations should be\n\nglobal so that when considering HOW to reach targets the Commission must consider the environmental costs (if any) of meeting\ntargets including, for example, pollution generated by the production of solar panels. We should also consider and be responsible our\n\nconsumption of imported goods that are arriving from developed countries that have not set targets. We don't want to be in the\nposition of essentially exporting our emissions. Options assessments should consider these factors"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It should also advise on options (incl costs and benefits) on HOW to achieve targets/budgets. This should include advice on our\n\nimpact on global emissions based on our consumption of imports. We should not be relying on other governments in terms of how\nour imports impact global emissions. The Commission should be able to advise government on this matter (essentially trade matters)"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "With government having to clearly explain deviations from that advice"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I'd also like to see Ecologists, experts in international/global climate policy, International law and someone who can advise on trade\nissues."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think legislation around adapting to climate change should be incorporated into the RMA and the local Government Acts (alongside\na boost in funding). This Bill should focus on reducing our impact ON climate change not the effects OF climate change."
    }
  ]
}
